Hillcrest Children's Center (Washington, D.C.) Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Hillcrest Children's Center (Washington, D.C.) Records 1815-1966 (bulk 1880-1960)
MSS54916
Hillcrest Children's Center (Washington, D.C.)
Hillcrest Children's Village (Washington, D.C.)
Washington City Orphan Asylum (Washington, D.C.)
Washington Female Orphan Asylum (Washington, D.C.)
9,500 items
54 containers plus 5 oversize
22 linear feet
1 microfilm reel
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Founded in 1815 as the Washington Female Orphan Asylum to care for girls left homeless by the British invasion of Washington, D.C., during the War of 1812. Official name changed to Washington City Orphan Asylum in 1828. Unofficially renamed Hillcrest Children's Village (1927-1953) and Hillcrest Children's Center (1953- ). Provided for the care and protection of homeless youths until 1953 and afterward for the treatment of emotionally disturbed children. Correspondence, minutes of meetings, committee and staff reports, admittance and application records, journals, ledgers, financial statements, deeds, mortgages, bank checks, budget estimates, index cards, and miscellaneous material reflecting the financial and managerial techniques of the center.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
Organizations
Children's House (Bethesda, Md.); Hillcrest Children's Center (Washington, D.C.); Hillcrest Children's Center (Washington, D.C.). Hillcrest Children's Center (Washington, D.C.) records. 1953-1966.; Hillcrest Children's Village (Washington, D.C.) Hillcrest Children's Village (Washington, D.C.) records. 1927-1953.; Washington City Orphan Asylum (Washington, D.C.). Washington City Orphan Asylum (Washington, D.C.) records. 1828-1927.; Washington Female Orphan Asylum (Washington, D.C.). Washington Female Orphan Asylum (Washington, D.C.) records. 1815-1828.; Washington Institute of Mental Hygiene.
Subjects
Child welfare--Washington (D.C.); Children--Institutional care--Washington (D.C.); Mentally ill children--Care--Washington (D.C)
Provenance
The records of Hillcrest Children's Center, Washington, D.C., were given to the Library of Congress by the center in 1968.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these records.
Access and Restrictions
The records of Hillcrest Children's Center are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on one reel. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Hillcrest Children's Center span the years 1815-1966, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1880-1960. Largely administrative, the records reflect the financial and managerial techniques of the institution that until the 1950s provided for the care and protection of homeless youths and in subsequent years for the treatment of emotionally disturbed children. The records include correspondence, minutes of meetings, committee and staff reports, admittance and application records, indentures, journals, ledgers, financial statements, deeds, mortgages, bank checks, budget estimates, index cards, and miscellaneous material.
The records have been organized into three series: Unbound Records, Bound Records, and Miscellany (Oversize). The Unbound Records are further subdivided into seven numerically classified categories: general records (100s), children's records (200s), lady managers' records (300s), trustees' records (400s-500s), property records (600s-700s), legacy and gift records (800s), and historical and miscellaneous records (900s). The numerical classification system, which also extends to the other two series, was designed by Dorothy Smith Coleman for the center in 1953 and has been left largely intact with only minor revisions and processing refinements.
The Washington Female Orphan Asylum, Hillcrest Center's original name when it was founded in 1815, was initially established to care for girls left homeless by the British invasion of the capital during the War of 1812 [1]. In the years since its founding, many Washington notables, including Dolly Madison (the center's first director), Marcia and John Van Ness, William Corcoran, and Blair Lee, among others, have contributed to the success of the institution as trustees or members of the Board of Lady Managers. Documentation relating to the early history of the institution is scanty and can be found chiefly in the minutes of the meetings of the Board of Lady Managers.
1. In 1828 the institution's name was changed “forever” by act of Congress (May 24) to the Washington City Orphan Asylum. Though Washington City Orphan Asylum still remains its official name, the institution was called Hillcrest Children's Village from 1927 to 1953 and Hillcrest Children's Center since 1953.
Traditionally the administration of the asylum rested with a Board of Lady Managers, charged with supervising the daily management of the institution and the care of the children, andwith five male trustees, whose duties included financial and property management. Of the two administrative units, the ladies' records are the more varied and complete, especially after the turn of the century. Of prime importance to the ladies' records are the minutes of the meetings which contain much of the basic information abstracted for the annual reports. The minutes contain correspondence, directives, committee and staff reports, resolutions, and memoranda prepared for and included as a result of the meetings. Other informative data concerning the lady managers, as well as the children receiving services, will be found in the staff and committee reports which, for the most part, are organized separately. Staffing, budgeting, maintenance, and medical services available for the children are the central points depicted in the superintendent and staff reports for the period 1933-1956. Beginning in the 1930s, a social worker prepared reports for the case committee detailing information on the applicants and residents. This information, in the form of case histories, describes to some degree the child's family background and personality traits. The lady managers' records also include reports of the Grounds and Educational Committees, journals listing the amount of overhead such as staff salaries and plant maintenance, and financial records pertaining to the Hillcrest home on Nebraska Avenue, N.W.
The records relating to the trustees are primarily financial in character, reflecting their role as budget directors and property managers. Although incomplete, the files include minutes of meetings, ledgers, journals, auditors' reports, promissory notes, and some correspondence. The property records, which comprise a separate series, greatly augment the fragmentary trustees' file and contain a wealth of information focused equally between investment properties and the asylum's residences.
The property records, while lacking in correspondence, reflect land values, building, repair, and rental costs in Washington, especially for the years 1870-1900. The trustee and property records and the files relating to legacies form the core of the center's financial records for the middle period and later years.
A significant though limited amount of material remains in the collection relating to the merger of Hillcrest with the Washington Institute of Mental Hygiene and Children's House. Documentation supplied by the annual reports and the ladies' minutes outlines the merger procedure which took place over the period 1953-1961. The superintendent's reports, together with information supplied by the case histories, treat with detail the staff's growing conviction that psychological treatment of children took precedence over other considerations. Consequently, in 1953 Hillcrest formed a working arrangement with the above-mentioned institutions to care exclusively for emotionally disturbed children. In 1961, after a report prepared by the Community Research Center of New York, the separate institutions merged under one administration.
Rounding out the collection are three file groups entitled children, general, and miscellaneous records. Files within these groups contain references to adoptions, indentures, constitutions, bylaws, annual and biennial reports, early acts of Congress relating to the formative years of the institution, historical sketches of the asylum, and complete description of the archives by Coleman.
In addition to the numerical classification outlined above, there is a further decimal classification for some of the records (see the first folder in Container 1 for details). Generally, the numerical classification is followed by three letters as described below:
Alphabetical Key
The alphabetical key classifies documents or file groups into three component parts: administrative relationship, chronological time span, and type of material.
T-Trustees A-1815-1865 B-Bound volume
L-Ladies D-1866-1875 F-Folder *
O-Both ladies and trustees S-1876-1925 E-Window binder *
H-1926- R-Looseleaf binder *
C-A combination of two or more periods N-Newspaper clippings
P-Pamphlet
*All documents formerly in looseleaf and window binders have been placed into folders and should be considered under the “F” classification. Consequently, all materials labeled E, R, or F are contained in the Unbound Records.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
Unbound Records, 1815-1966
Bound Records, 1815-1955
Miscellany (Oversize)
Container List
- Unbound Records, 1815-1966 (Boxes 1-33)
  Correspondence, minutes of meetings, committee and staff reports, accounting statements, bills, receipts, canceled checks, notes, list, vouchers, deeds, titles, blueprints, tax and rent receipts, legal opinions, and printed matter.
  Numerically arranged and decimally cataloged within seven major groupings.
  - General records (Box 1)
    - File code key and archives data, 1953, 100 0CF
    - Archives, reports and correspondence
      - 1952, 100.1-100.2
      - 1953, 100.2-OHF
    - Affidavit, management funds and taxes, 1947, 101
    - Merger, Washington Institute of Mental Hygiene, 1952-1953, 102 OHF
    - Acts of Congress, constitutions and bylaws, 113 OCF
    - Photocopy of constitution and early relinquishments, 113.1 OCF
    - Amendments of constitution and by laws
      - 1937, 113.2 OCF
      - 1948, 114 OHF
    - Authority of ladies versus trustees, 1896, 1939, 115 OCF
    - Constitution, bylaws, acts of Congress (copies and pamphlets), 130 OCF
    - Authority under charter, 1901, 131 TSF
    - 1874 amendment to Act, 132 TDF
    - Congressional appropriation, 1876, 133 TSF
    - Public welfare legislation, 1924, 134 OSF
    - 1933 amendment to Act, 1930-1933, 135 TSF
    - Free water,act of Congress, 136 OSF (Box 2)
    - Annual reports, 1840-1860, 151 LAE
    - Annual reports at Public Library,correspondence concerning, 1932, 1935, 154 OCF
    - Annual reports, 1838, 155 OCE
    - Ladies and trustees,correspondence, 1866-1951, 180 OCF
    - Operating expenses,Hillcrest, 1924-1930, 182 OHF
    - Washington City Orphan Asylum (WCOA), name controversy, 1926, 190 OHF
    - Child Welfare League, WCOA report, 1937, 191 OHF
    - Washington Institute, Lucia Whittemore study, 1952, 192 OHF
    - National Child Research Center, recommendations, 1942, 193 LHF
    - Annual administration announcement, sustaining members data, 1946, 194 OHF
    - Historical summary, speech of Ms. Arthur Wallace Dunn, 195 LHF
    - Flinn, Anne, note on life, 1827, 200 LAE
  - Children's records
    - Board of Public Welfare contracts, 1944-1948, 201 OHF
    - Payments by children's parents, 1941, 202 OHF
    - Lusby boys, 203 OSF
    - Board of Children's Guardians, 204 LSF
    - Admission of children, reference letters, 1876-1922, 216 LCF
    - Juvenile Court commitment orders, 1909-1910, 217 OSF
    - Government application for admissions, 218 LSF
    - Indian captive from Idaho, 1882, 1892, 225 LSF
    - Application for admission, 1908-1923, 226 LSF
    - Children's activities, “Sparks,” 1932-1949, 230 LHF
    - Little Museum News, 1936-1950, 231 LHF (Box 3)
    - Kindergarten, 1896, 232 LSF
    - Kindergarten and Gould monthly report, 1935-1943, 233 LHF
    - Application for return of children to parents, 240 LSF
    - Return of children to parents, 1918, 241 LSF
    - Legal custody of child, 1918, 242 LSF
    - Indentures for binding out children, 1851-1854, 250 LAF
    - Indentures, adoptions, court orders, 1870-1923, 1941, 255 LSF
    - Legality of apprenticing outside of the District of Columbia, 256 TSF
    - Binding out of Sturgis children, 1864-1869, 257 LCF
    - Indentures and adoptions, correspondence, 258 LCF
    - Adoption of Elizabeth Keyes by Admiral Hooper, 1941-1944, 261 LHF
    - Reference letters, adoption of children, 1897-1918, 262 LCF
    - Applications for adoption, 1906-1913, 263 LCF
    - Adoption of children, legal questions, 1942, 1947, 264 OHF
    - Orphan's picture, 1898, 270 DSE
    - Letters from children, 1871-1941, 280 LCF
    - Adult accomplishments of former inmates, 1910-1930, 281 LCF
    - James E. West, 282 LCF
    - Boys in service, 1917-1918, Miss Colt's note, 283 LSF
    - Care of European refugee children, 1940, 291 OHF
    - Death certificates, 1872-1896, 292 OCF
    - Doctors for asylum, 1870-1940, 292 LCF
    - Children, miscellaneous, 1872-1947, 294 LCF
    - Genealogical data, legal adoption, 1876-1942, 295 LCF
    - Children, involved cases, correspondence relating to, 296 LCF
    - Benet psychology test, 297 LHF
    - Menu, 1951, 298 LHF
  - Lady managers' records (Box 4)
    - First directress or secretary, annual report, 300 LHF
    - Case Committee
      - Annual report, 301 LHF
      - Reports, 1938-1944, 301.1 LHF
      - Reports, 1945-1949, 1951-1952, 301.1 LHF
    - Education Committee (Box 5)
      - Annual reports, 1938-1951, 302 LHF
      - Reports, 1938-1940, 302.2 LHF
    - Membership Committee, annual reports, 1946-1949, 304 LHF
    - Archives Committee, annual reports, 1915, 1937, 1954, 1956, 305 LHF
    - Little Museum, annual reports, 1938-1951, 306 LHF
    - Grounds Committee, annual reports, 1927-1952, 1954, 307 LHF
    - House Committee, annual reports, 1923-1951, 308 LHF
    - Finance Committee, annual reports, 1923-1951, 308 LHF
    - Future Plans Committee, reports and data, 1938-1951, 309.1 LHF
    - Minutes of meetings of the Board of Directors
      - 1953-June 1958, 317 LHF
      - July 1958-1960, 317 LHF (Box 6)
    - Superintendent and staff
      - Annual and monthly reports
        - 1933-1940, 330 LHF
        - 1941-1956, 330 LHF (Box 7)
    - Employees, injuries and retirement, 1930-1947, 331 LHF
    - Teachers, 1862, 1896, 332 LCF
    - Unemployment Compensation Board, Social Security
      - 1938-1947, 333 LHF
      - 1936-1937, 333.1 LHF
    - Staff, contracts, duties, recommendations, etc., 1932-1942, 334 LHF (Box 8)
    - Social worker's annual and monthly reports, 1941-1950, 335 LHF
    - Ladies' accounts
      - Auditor's reports
        - 1923-1932, 346.1 LCF
        - 1933-1938, 346.1 LCF (Box 9)
        - 1939-1959, 346.2 LHF
    - Treasurers' annual reports, lady managers
      - 1921-1931, 346.3 LCF
      - 1932-1940, 346.4 LHF
      - 1941-1948, 346.4 LHF
    - Treasurers' monthly reports, lady managers, 1957-1960, 346.7 LHF (Box 10)
    - Maintenance, beneficiary, and Hillcrest journals See Container 59 (Oversize), 347
    - Hillcrest, payroll records and control sheets, 1951-1960, 347.1 LHF
    - Investments of ladies, 1927-1950, 348
    - Ladies, miscellaneous financial data, 1926-1950, 349.1 LCF
    - Miss Colt, miscellaneous financial data, 1927-1939, 349.2 LCF (Box 11)
    - Original subscription paper for additional building, 1856, 353 OAE
    - Budget estimates, 1923-1951, 370 LHF
    - Increased expenditures, correspondence, 1924, 1935, 1950, 371 OSF
    - Titcomb to Bomford letter concerning position, 1834, 380 LAE
    - Letters concerning Ladies' Board, 1941-1950, 382 LCF
  - Trustees' records (Box 12)
    - Minutes of the meetings of the Board of Trustees
      - 1843-1922, 410 TCF
      - 1923-1926, 411 TSF
      - 1927-1933, 412 THF
      - 1935-1946, 413 THF
      - 1843-1926 (originals), 415 TCF
    - Legal opinion of Richard S. Coxe, 1828, 430 LAE
    - Legal opinion of James Wilkes, 1952, 432 OHF
    - Larned to French correspondence concerning French's election to Board of Trustees, 1845, 480 TAE
    - Trustees' letters, 1845-1948, 481 TCF
    - Hall and Temple's visit to St. Vincent, 1875, 490 TDF
    - Trustees' accounts, condensed statement, 1875, 1878-1884, 501 TCF
    - Statement showing yearly balance, 1892-1933, 1935-1936, 502 TCP
    - Auditor's reports
      - 1928-1943, 503 THF
      - 1927, 503 THF (Box 13)
    - Safe deposit box notations, 1888, 1912-1947, 504 TCF
    - Assets, income, expenses, 1931, 505 THF
    - Miscellaneous account of John Van Ness
      - 1829, 510 TAE
      - 1834, 510.2 TAE
    - Account of A. C. Smith, 1840, 511 TAE
    - Bank books, Bank of Metropolis, 1831-1841, 515 TAE
    - Bank books, 1849, 1876-1882, 515.1 TCF
    - Trustees' accounts, journals
      - 1849-1858, 520 TAF
      - 1859-1870, 522 TCF
      - 1872, 523 TDF
      - 1874-1878, 524 TCF
      - 1879-1882, 525 TSF
      - 1883-1884, 1887, 526 TSF (Box 14)
    - Vouchers
      - 1898-1904, 533 TSF
      - 1907-1908, 534 TSF
    - Rent, accounts, taxes, and assessments, 1898-1909, 535 TSF
    - Trustees' accounts
      - Property, 1833-1851, 540 TAF
      - Securities, 1836-1851, 541 TAF
      - Promissory notes, 1833-1851, 542 TAF
      - Property, 1868, etc., 543 TCF
      - Securities, 1853-1874, 544 TCF (Box 15)
    - Stocks and bonds, 1873-1902, and miscellaneous, 544.1
    - Trustees' accounts
      - Memoranda on notes, 1852-1874, 545 TCF
      - Indentures, 1860-1886, 546 TCF
      - Securities and notes, 1872-1874, 547 TDF
      - Securities, 1872-1885, 549 TCF
    - Promissory notes, correspondence, etc.
      - 1870-1890 and undated, 549.1 TSF
      - 1891-1906, 556 TSF
    - Stocks and bonds
      - 1924-1945, 557 TCF
      - 1947, 558 THF
    - Savings and loan association accounts, 559 THF
    - Mortgage notes, 1898, 559.1 TSF
    - Laurie Fund (Box 16)
      - Property left by Hall, 560 TSF
      - Treasurer's account, 1882-1884, 1887, 561 TSF
    - Dividends credited to Snow Fund by mistake, 570 THF
    - Monthly statements, National Savings and Trust Co.
      - 1949-1952, 571 LHF
      - 1949-1950, 572 THF
      - 1951, 573 THF
    - Larned to Stone letter concerning finances, 1846, 580 TAE
    - Treasurer's correspondence
      - 1843-1851, 582 TAF
      - 1852-1896, 1900, 583 TCF
    - Asylum debt to John Van Ness, 1820-1821, 590 OAE
    - James Larned notation concerning Bomford estate, 590.1 TAE
    - Money borrowed by asylum, 1851-1872, 591 TCF
    - Income of Alexandria Orphan Asylum, 1882, 592 TSF
    - Miscellaneous bills, 1868-1892, 594 OCF
    - Banks' checks, 1833-1901, 595 TCF
    - WCOA v Tucker, non payment of promissory note, 1894, 597 TSF
    - Direction concerning entries in books, deposits, etc., 1906, 598 TSF
    - Blair Lee, trustee v Elizabeth Mitcham, 1937, 599 THF
  - Property records (Box 17)
    - 7th Street property
      - Deed, 1816, 610 TAE
    - H Street property
      - Gales to Van Ness, 1826, 620 OAE
      - Deed, Jan. 1829, 621 OAE
      - Deed, Aug. 1829, 622 OAE
      - Construction costs, 1828-1829, 623 TAE
      - Miscellany, 1840-1879, 625 TAF
      - Repairs, 1836-1849, 626 TAF
      - Addition, 1856-1857, 628 TAF
  - Lee house in Douglas row
    - House rented, 1866-1876, 630 TDF
    - Repairs, 1866-1875, 631 TDF
  - 14th and S Street property
    - Deed and title, 640 TSF
    - Construction of building, 641 TSF
    - Rented to State Department, 1886-1887, 642 TSF
    - Iron railing, 643 OSF
    - Taxes and assessments, 1870-1893, 1917, and 1927, 644 TSF
    - Street addition, 1881-1882, 645 TSF
    - Alterations, 1886-1887, 646 TSF
    - Repairs
      - 1876, 647 TSF
      - 1877-1890, 648 TSF (Box 18)
      - 1891-1900, 649 TSF
      - 1901-1910, 650 TSF
      - 1911-1926, 651 TSF
      - Blueprint of basement and first floor, 653 TSF
      - Value of asylum, 654 OSF
      - Petition for rezoning Sq. 239, 655 TSF
      - Offers to buy asylum, 1923-1926, 656 TSF
      - Sale of asylum buildings, 657 TSF
      - Notes of James L. Karrick, 1927-1942, 658 TSF
      - Miscellaneous, 1865-1904, 659 OSF
    - Hillcrest
      - Purchase, 1922-1926, 660-661.1 THF
      - Land adjoining property, 662 THF (Box 19)
      - Request for bids, 1923-1925, 663 THF
      - Specifications for Hillcrest, 664 THF
      - Correspondence, proposed building, 1919-1926, 665 THF
      - Trip to New York, minutes, 666 LHF
      - Taxation, 1925-1947, 667 THF
      - Contract for new building, 668 THF
      - Vouchers for building, 669 THF
      - Change from heating oil to coal, war conservation, 1943-1945, 669.1 THF
      - Correspondence, building, 670 THF
      - Occupancy permit, zoning, 670.1 OHF
      - Unlawful use of premises, 1923, 670.2 THF
      - Strip sold through property, 1952, 671 THF
      - Condemnation of parcel 34/102, 672 THF
      - Closing of Loughboro Road, 1930, 672.1 THF (Box 20)
      - Van Ness Street condemnation for widening street, 1929-1934, 672.2 THF
      - Dedication of land, 1933, 1946, 672.3 THF
      - Sidewalk assessments, 1937-1942, 672.4 THF
      - Cottage built, 1930-1932, 673 OHF
      - Proposal for new building to house twenty boys, 1931, 673.1 OHF
      - Proposed Boy Scout house, 1942, 673.2 OHF
      - Proposed sale of land for TV tower, 1945, 673.3 THF
      - Outside repairs, 1921-1945, 674 THF
      - Boiler inspection, 1944, 1945-1946, 674.1 THF
      - Lightning strikes, 1940, 674.2 THF
      - Repairs and equipment
        - 1928, 675 THF
        - 1929, 675.1 THF
        - 1930, 675.2 THF
        - 1931, 675.3 THF
        - 1932, 675.4 THF
        - 1933, 675.5 THF
        - 1934, 675.6 THF
        - 1935, 675.7 THF
        - 1936, 675.8 THF
        - 1937, 675.9 THF
        - 1938, 676 THF (Box 21)
        - 1939, 676.1 THF
        - 1940, 676.2 THF
        - 1941, 676.3 THF
        - 1942, 676.4 THF
        - 1943, 676.5 THF
        - 1944, 676.6 THF
        - 1945, 676.7 THF
        - 1946, 676.8 THF
        - 1947, 676.9 THF
        - 1948, 677 THF
      - Inventory, 1948, 677.1 LHF
      - Repairs and equipment
        - 1949, 677.2 THF
        - 1953, 677.3 THF
      - Landscaping and grounds, 1925-1931, 1947-1949, 678.1 LHF
      - Playground, 1928-1931, 687.2 LHF
    - Ingleside summer home, 1886, 680 OSF
    - Summer Camp Edwin Gould, 1927, 1930, 681 OSF
    - Proposal for new asylum home, 1897, 690 OSF
    - Real estate belonging to WCOA, 1895, 700 TSF (Box 22)
    - Rental properties, financial data, 1891-1896, 701 TSF
    - Insurance, fire and other, 1866-1919, 1922-1942, 730 OCF
    - Property taxes and assessments, 1860-1898, 731 TCF
    - Tax on corn and hogs requested, 732 THF
    - Report made to District of Columbia tax commissioners for tax, 733 TSF (Box 23)
    - Business privilege tax, 1939, 734 THF
    - Plot of lots assigned to WCOA by Congress, 1832, 742 TAE
    - Lots appropriated by Congress